A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Race and Ethnicity Task Force Files FA267
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Race and Ethnicity Task Force Files
1953-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA267
4.56 Cubic Feet 12 LTR size Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the files of the Ford Foundation's Race and Ethnicity Task Force. It consists of one series of subject files. Documents chiefly originate from between 1972 when the task force was first created as a result of Foundation President McGeorge Bundy advocating race and ethnicity as one of ten subjects for investigation in his "Planning for the Foundation's Program in 1973 and Beyond" discussion paper and 1974 when the task force submitted its final recommendations to the Foundation Board of Trustees. Reports, papers, and other types of materials originating from the 1950s and 1960s can also be found in the collection due to the task force's efforts to gather information on the state of research regarding the nature and role of race and ethnicity. The collection's contents appear to have been principally created and organized by the task force director Basil Whiting who served as a Program Officer for the Social Development Program in the National Affairs Division and by Shirley Teper, a consultant for the task force.
In addition to reports and papers, the collection contains materials such as correspondence, memos, agendas, schedules, participant lists, notes, expense reports, proposals, and an audio recording transcript of the February 1973 Race and Ethnicity Task Force retreat. These records document the task force's meetings and communications with scholars and institutions associated with race and ethnicity studies research as well discussions regarding the task force's final report. The task force engaged race and ethnicity related research from the fields of sociology, minority studies, anthropology, urban studies, cultural studies, and psychology and gathered information on topics such race relations, interethnic and interracial conflict, and cultural pluralism.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as part of Accession 2019:046 Ford Foundation records, Program Strategy records.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible during processing.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1953-1974
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Race and Ethnicity Task Force originated from a discussion paper titled "Planning for the Foundation's Program in 1973 and Beyond" that Foundation President McGeorge Bundy presented to the Foundation Board of Trustees in March 1972. Bundy placed race and ethnicity as the first of ten subjects the Foundation sought to investigate for the purpose of determining future programming priorities. Headed by Social Development Program Officer Basil Whiting, the Race and Ethnicity Task Force strived to assess the state of available research on the nature and role of race and ethnicity, especially in regards to the United States, and report its recommendations to the Trustees for a potential program on basic research on race and ethnicity. The task force was an internal team composed of Foundation staff members. Shirley Teper served as a consultant.
In its final report, the Race and Ethnicity Task Force recommended against the Ford Foundation initiating a program of basic research on race and ethnicity. Instead, it suggested that the Foundation develop an exploratory program on studies in racial, cultural, and political pluralism.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Ford Foundation; Cultural pluralism; Ethnology -- Study and teaching; Minorities -- Study and teaching; Race relations
- Subject files, 1953-1974; 1; 4.56 Cubic Feet 12 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files created through the activities of the Ford Foundation's Race and Ethnicity Task Force. It documents the task force's efforts to assess the state of research on race and ethnicity through background reports and papers, internal memos and correspondence, external communications with scholars and institutions from diverse fields on the topic of race and ethnicity, and collected grant proposals for projects related to race and ethnicity studies. Materials appear to have been chiefly created and organized by Social Development Program Officer Basil Whiting who headed the task force and by Shirley Teper, a consultant on the task force.
  Materials generally originate from between 1972 and 1974 when the Race and Ethnicity Task Force was active. Nevertheless, some of the reports and grant proposals collected by and submitted to the task force originate from as early as 1953. Race and Ethnicity Task Force and larger Ford Foundation memos and correspondence outline the purpose of the project and its relationship to the other Planning Agenda Task Forces, document administrative and operational activities, and discuss the preparation of the final report which the task force submitted to the Foundation Board of Trustees. The series of meetings convened by the task force to discuss different topics related to race and ethnicity are documented by meeting agendas and schedules, expense reports, correspondence with scholars who participated in the meetings, and papers from those scholars. The task force would ask meeting participants to prepare written statements on basic research in race and ethnicity, and participants would often later write about their reactions to the meetings to Whiting and Teper. Some of the grant proposals collected within the series were submitted directly to the task force, while others were forwarded from different programs at the foundation. Funding projects related to race and ethnicity studies was not actually within the scope of the task force's responsibilities. Nevertheless, there are some materials pertaining to earlier grants made by the Ford Foundation.
  The series also includes an audio recording transcript of the Race and Ethnicity Task Force February 1973 retreat.
  - Background to Task Force Study - Reports by Ford Foundation personnel/consultants, M-Z, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Background to Task Force Study - Reports by Non-Ford Foundation personnel/consultants, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
  - Conferences on race and ethnicity - Academy of Arts and Sciences seminar, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Conferences on race and ethnicity - The Center, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Conferences on race and ethnicity - Miscellaneous, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Conferences on race and ethnicity - Indiana University Office of Economic Opportunity Conference on Racial Discrimination, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Conferences on race and ethnicity - Miscellaneous, circa 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Background reading materials - Bibliographies and directories, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Task Force memorandum and first set of background papers, 1972 December 4 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Task Force retreat, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
  - Task Force readings, volume 2, 1973 June (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Consultants - Honoraria, expense reports, letters of consultancy, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Task Force readings, volume 1, 1973 June (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Memoranda - Basil Whiting, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
  - Consultants - Honoraria, expense reports, letters of consultancy, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous reports, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Task Force retreat, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
  - Task Force retreat transcript, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 32-34)
  - Task Force meetings, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 35-36)
  - Task Force June 1973 meetings - History, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Task Force June 1973 meetings - Labor, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Task Force June 1973 meetings - Black and ethnic studies, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 39-40)
  - Task Force June 1973 meetings - Minority sociologists (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Task Force June 1973 meetings - Anthropology (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Task Force May 1973 meetings - Research methodology (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Task Force May 1973 meetings - Group identity (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Task Force May 1973 meetings - International dimensions, 1968-1973 (Box 7, Folder 45-46)
  - Task Force May 1973 meetings - Social policy (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Task Force May 1973 meetings - Daniel Thompson (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Task Force May 1973 meetings - Sociology, 1966-1973 (Box 8, Folder 49-51)
  - Task Force April 1973 meetings - Psychology and social psychology, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Task Force April 1973 meetings - Albert Scheflen and anthropological proposal (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Task Force April 1973 meetings - Kalman Silvert (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Task Force April 1973 meetings - North Carolina Agricultural and Technical College (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - National Center for Urban Ethnic Affairs, Geno Baroni, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 56-57)
  - Task Force March 1973 meetings - Paul Wrobel (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Task Force March 1973 meetings - National Opinion Research Center (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Task Force March 1973 meetings - National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)/National Science Foundation (NSF), 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Task Force December 1972 meeting - Ethnic Conference, Chicago, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Allegheny Academy, Peter Sustar, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, Kenyon Burke, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, Oscar Cohen, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Brandeis University, Lemberg Center for the Study of Violence, John Spiegel, 1964-1973 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - University of California Los Angeles, Judith Caditz, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Carleton University, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Center for the Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Adam Podgorecki, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - University of Connecticut, Harold Abramson, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Cornell University, Leonard Reissman, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Curtis, Lynn A., 1973 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - Ethnic Heritage Affairs Institute, Inc., 1973 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Grant proposals, A-E - The Ethnic Foundation, Paul Deac, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Harvard University, Geoffrey Bock, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Harvard University, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Hillcrest Children's Center, Reginald S. Lourie, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Anthony M. Orum, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Institute of Comparative Ethnic Studies, 1974; File includes a still image glued to a piece of paper in a proposal. (Box 10, Folder 78-79)
    The still image in the file is a photograph taken of the January 14, 1973 Project Interviewers' meeting of the Topeka Intercultural Research Project.
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Jewish Association for College Youth, Steven Windmueller, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Kent State University, Giles Edward Gobetz, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Grant proposals, H-K - Janowsky, Oscar I., 1973 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - McCraw, Morgan E., 1973 (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - Miller, James, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - University of Minnesota, Paul Pedersen, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - University of Minnesota, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - National Academy of Sciences, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - National Opinion Research Center, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - University of New Mexico, Marc H. Irwin, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - North Carolina State University, William Maxwell, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 90)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - Northwestern University, Francis Hsu, 1953-1973 (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Grant proposals, M-O - Ohio University, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Parming, Tonu, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 93)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Alicia Patterson Foundation, Susan Jacoby, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - University of Pittsburgh, Carl Beck, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America, Inc., Eugene Kleban, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 96)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Prpic, George, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 97)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Race Relations Information Center, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - University of Texas at El Paso, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Urban Institute, undated (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Vroman, Wayne, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - Grant proposals, P-Z - Washington University, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - Interoffice memoranda, 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 103-104)
  - General correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 105-106)
  - Correspondence from foundations, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - Background to Task Force Study - Reports by Ford Foundation personnel/consultants, A-L, 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 108-111)